From Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia
For the 1889 Universal Telegraphic Phrase-book, see Commercial code (communications).
This article contains special characters. Without proper rendering support, you may see question marks, boxes, or other symbols.


Unicode is a computing industry standard for the consistent encoding, representation, and handling of text expressed in most of the world's writing systems. Developed in conjunction with the Universal Character Set standard and published as The Unicode Standard, the latest version of Unicode contains a repertoire of more than 110,000 characters covering 100 scripts and multiple symbol sets. The standard consists of a set of code charts for visual reference, an encoding method and set of standard character encodings, a set of reference data computer files, and a number of related items, such as character properties, rules for normalization, decomposition, collation, rendering, and bidirectional display order (for the correct display of text containing both right-to-left scripts, such as Arabic and Hebrew, and left-to-right scripts).[1] As of June 2014, the most recent version is Unicode 7.0. The standard is maintained by the Unicode Consortium.

Unicode's success at unifying character sets has led to its widespread and predominant use in the internationalization and localization of computer software. The standard has been implemented in many recent technologies, including modern operating systems, XML, the Java programming language, and the Microsoft .NET Framework.

Unicode can be implemented by different character encodings. The most commonly used encodings are UTF-8, UTF-16 and the now-obsolete UCS-2. UTF-8 uses one byte for any ASCII character, all of which have the same code values in both UTF-8 and ASCII encoding, and up to four bytes for other characters. UCS-2 uses a 16-bit code unit (two 8-bit bytes) for each character but cannot encode every character in the current Unicode standard. UTF-16 extends UCS-2, using one 16-bit unit for the characters that were representable in UCS-2 and two 16-bit units (4 × 8 bit) to handle each of the additional characters.


Unicode は世界で使われる全ての文字を共通の文字集合にて利用できるようにしようという考えで作られ、Unix、Windows、Mac OS X、Plan 9[2]、Javaなどで利用されている。
Unicodeでは、文字集合中の文字をあらわす符号位置（コードポイント、符号点を参照）に、「Unicodeスカラ値」という非負整数値が割り振られている。Unicodeスカラ値は "U+" の後に十六進法でその値を続けることで表す。BMP内の符号位置は U+0000 〜 U+FFFF の4桁で表すことができ、SMP以降は5桁または6桁を必要とする。
収録されている文字は、各国で標準として規定されている文字集合や実際に使用されている文字を持ち寄り、委員会により取捨選択されている。日本の文字については当初より JIS X 0201、JIS X 0208 と補助漢字を、Unicode 3.1 では JIS X 0213 の内容も収録している。
また収録において、元の各文字集合内で分離されている文字は尊重するが、異なる文字集合に同一の文字が収録されているとみなされるものは、同じ符号位置に割り当てる方針を取っている。この際に集合が膨大であるという理由で、漢字について、中国、日本、韓国の各規格の漢字を統合（英語版）しCJK統合漢字としたことは大きな議論となった。
Unicodeでは文字符号化方式も標準化したため、従来見られたShift JISとEUC-JPとの間の混乱のようなものは回避されている。
Unicode以前の文字コードとの相互運用性もある程度考慮されており、歴史上・実用上の識別が求められる場合には互換領域がとられ、元のコード→Unicode→元のコードというような変換（ラウンドトリップ変換）において、元通りに戻るよう配慮されている文字もある。しかし、正規のJIS X 0208の範囲内であればトラブルは少ないが、複数の文字集合が混在したり、Shift JISの実態であるCP932やEUC-JPの亜種であるCP51932とeucJP-MSなど、対応が違うために文字化けを起こすことがある。


統一碼（Unicode），又叫做萬國碼同單一碼，係一種國際標準電腦文字編碼，用來畀電腦儲存同交換文字訊息。電腦要將文字編碼，即係每個字畀個數字佢。
響未有統一碼之前，世界各地都用唔同嘅編碼，搞到好難互換資料。有時同一種語言，咁多種編碼都無辦法包括晒日常生活要用字。整統一碼出來，就係畀全世界嘅電腦有一種共用嘅編碼，可以好方便咁交換資料。
現時統一碼嘅發展係由統一碼聯盟負責，佢嘅同ISO/IEC有好緊密嘅聯繫。統一碼同國際標準ISO/IEC 10646係一致嘅。
統一碼嘅出現，幫助軟件可以進一步國際化同本地方化。亦都容許唔同地方嘅文字擺埋一齊。